Now when we are done with the project,
والآن ومع الانتهاء من المشروع،
it becomes important for us to be on the same page with the client,
من المهم أن نكون على وفاق مع العميل،
so that both parties agree that the requirements have been met.
حيث يجب أن يكونا الطرفان متفقان أنه تم استيفاء المتطلبات.
Now this becomes important for two reasons.
وهذا أمر هام لسببين.
Especially in fixed cost projects,
خاصة في المشاريع التي تعمل بنظام التكلفة الثابتة،
your final payment from the client could be blocked until the client
فقد يتم حجب استحقاقك المالي لحين تأكيد
confirms that all the requirements in the project scope have been met.
العميل استيفاء كافة المتطلبات في إطار المشروع.
Second, it formally ends the project and
وثانيًا، فهذا الاتفاق يعني انتهاء المشروع رسميًا،
marks an end to the time that you need to spend on the project,
وينهي الفترة الزمنية للعمل على المشروع
so now you can allocate your time to other projects.
وبهذا تستطيع استخدام وقتك للعمل على مشاريع أخرى.
You don't want the client to keep coming back to you with small fixes even after
فلن تريد بالطبع أن يبقى الأمر مفتوحًا، فيعود لك العميل طالبًا بعض التعديلات البسيطة بعد
a month of finishing the project just
شهر من انتهاء المشروع،
because the client got delayed in validating the solution.
فقط لأن العميل تأخر في التحقق من إتمام الحلول التي قدمتها للمشروع.
For fixed cost projects,
بالنسبة لمشاريع التكلفة الثابتة،
that could mean you spending extra time for the claim for an indefinite period of time.
فهذا قد يعني أنك ستقضي وقتًا إضافيًا حيث أن المشروع لا يعمل بنظام المدة المحددة.
For time and materials project,
أما بالنسبة للمشاريع التي تعمل بنظام قياس الوقت والجهد،
that could mean extra revenue for you but could also be
فهذا قد يعني أنك ستتلقى عائد أكبر ولكن قد يعني أيضًا
a distraction if you're working on other larger project that needs your attention.
تشتيت للانتباه في حال كنت تعمل على مشاريع أكبر تتطلب تركيزك.
Now in order to meet the deliverable complete and not keep the project lingering,
والآن حتى تُنهي متطلبات المشروع ولا تُبقي الأمر مُعلق
there are two things that we can do.
هنا أمرين نستطيع عملهما.
First, it is important to communicate in writing that from your perspective,
الأول: من المهم أن تتواصل كتابيًا وتوضح أنه من طرفك
you have completed the project,
قد أتممت العمل على المشروع،
but the client is free to come back and let
ولكن للعميل الحرية الكاملة في العودة لك مرة أخرى
you know if they think that there are things to be done.
ليخبرك إن كان هناك أي طلبات يريد تكملتها.
For example, there may be bugs in the software application,
فعلى سبيل المثال، قد يكون هناك خطأ برمجي في التطبيق،
you bet, or workstreams left out in a digital marketing solution.
أو عدم استيفاء مسار ما في حلول التسويق الإلكتروني.
Why is this important?
ما أهمية ذلك؟
This helps with two things.
هذا التواصل الكتابي يساعدك في أمرين.
First, it creates a record of you informing the client that the work is done.
أولًا، يُعتبر توثيق بأنك أخبرت العميل بأنك أنهيت عملك.
Second, it puts a timestamp on when you are done with the work.
ثانيًا، يضع حدًا زمنيًا لإنهاء العمل.
It is generally a good idea for this to be sent from
وهذه فكرة جيدة جدًا بأن تبعث هذه الرسالة
your own email account and not just
من بريدك الإلكتروني وليس فقط
mentioned in a project management tool or a communication tool
عن طريق أدوات المشروع أو وسائل الاتصال الأخرى
like Skype so that you have a permanent record of that communication even
محادثات مثل Skype، فعن طريق البريد الإلكتروني ستحتفظ بتوثيق للأمر يبقى معك حتى
after you leave the project and no longer have access to clients communication tools.
بعد غلق المشروع وعدم استطاعتك الوصول للعميل بأدوات المشروع.
If the client gave you a separate email address to communicate with,
إذا أعطاك العميل عنوان بريد إلكتروني منفصل للتواصل معه،
you could send email from that email address and cc your own email address,
يمكنك إرسال بريد إلكتروني له، ونسخة cc إلى عنوان البريد الإلكتروني الخاص بك،
so you have a record.
حتى تحتفظ بتوثيق للأمر.
If needed, you can mention it to the client so they're okay with it.
إذا دعت الحاجة، يمكنك ذكر ذلك إلى العميل حتى تتأكد من عدم ممانعته.
Secondly, we need to make sure to set a timeline
ثانيا، علينا أن نتأكد من تحديد جدول زمني
until which the client can come back to you instead of keeping it indefinite.
يستطيع العميل خلاله العودة لك بحيث لا يُترك الأمر مفتوحًا إلى أجل غير مسمى.
For example, you can say that the client is free to come
على سبيل المثال، يمكنك القول أن العميل يستطيع الرجوع إليك
back within 48 hours of delivery of the final submission,
خلال 48 ساعة من الاستلام النهائي للمشروع
in case they have any issues with it.
في حال كان له أي طلب أو تعديل.
If you have a contract or a service agreement with the client,
إذا كان هناك عقد أو اتفاق مع العميل،
it is a good idea to put this clause in there.
فوضع هذا البند في العقد فكرة جيدة.
If not, you can put it nicely in
إن لم يكن هناك عقد، فيمكنك إرسال هذه النقطة بشكل لائق
the email that you send to the client for the final submission,
في بريد إلكتروني وإرساله للعميل مع التسليم النهائي
so they know that they have to get back within a definite time period.
حتى يعرف أن عليه العودة إليك فقط خلال فترة زمنية محددة.
This will help set a deadline to your availability for the project,
وهذا سيساعد على تحديد موعد نهائي لعملك على المشروع،
and you can avoid a scenario where the client
ويمكنك تجنب سيناريو حيث يستمر العميل
keeps coming back to you even after a month of delivery,
في العودة إليك حتى بعد شهر من التسليم،
finding issues in your work that you may feel obligated to fix.
وإيجاد مشكلات في عملك وقد تشعر أنك ملزم بإصلاحها.